Finding Aid for Albert D. English papers, 1839-1957
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Albert D. English papers 1839-1957
English, Albert D., 1862-
2 linear feet
85850 Aa 2
Manchester Township, Washtenaw County, Michigan, farmer. Material concerning farming activities, his work with the Southern Washtenaw Farmers' Club, local Democratic Party affairs, his work as clerk of the Iron Creek (Manchester Township) Free Will Baptist Church; correspondence including letter from former slave Thomas English of West Virginia; also miscellaneous account books of family members, notebooks containing reference information, and reports of the overseer of highways for Manchester Township; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Edward Wisner (donor no. 3113 ). The bulk of the collection came to the library in 1975.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Born in Manchester, Michigan in 1862, Albert D. English became a prosperous Washtenaw County farmer and church leader. Though English seldom ventured beyond his local community, he had a wide range of interests. He was active in the Free Will Baptist Church, serving for several years as clerk of the Iron Creek Church. In addition, he was secretary of the Southern Washtenaw Farmers' Club, school inspector for the Manchester school system (English was teacher for one year), overseer of Manchester's highways, and active local Democratic Party worker.
The English collection documents each of these phases of his life, and provides the researcher with valuable material for the study of Manchester between 1880 and 1910. In addition to correspondence, the collection includes notebooks containing the newspaper columns on local affairs which English wrote for several county newspapers. There are also 18 "Ready Reference Books" containing lists of local, state, and national political candidates and office holders, Manchester property owners, lists of school teachers and graduates, church leaders, as well as other information gleaned from almanacs and newspapers over the years. Included are also several farm journals of A.D. English and his father Benjamin English, and a personal diary of English's sister, Lucy. Though much of the correspondence files concerns the Free Will Baptist Church, there is one unusual letter from a former slave, Thomas English of West Virginia, whom A.D. English apparently contacted in regard to the family genealogy. There is no record of continued correspondence on this subject.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Free Will Baptists (1780?-1911)--Michigan--Manchester.; Freedmen--West Virginia.; Manchester (Mich.); Manchester (Mich.: Township); Roads--Michigan--Manchester (Township); Southern Washtenaw Farmers' Club.; Washtenaw County (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
India--Missions.; Missionaries--India.; Missions--India.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1844, 1873-1920, and 1948
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1844 1873-1875 (Box 1)
  - 1886-1887 (Box 1)
  - 1888 (Box 1)
  - 1889 (Box 1)
  - 1890 (Box 1)
  - 1891 (Box 1)
  - 1892 (Box 1)
  - 1893 (Box 1)
  - 1894 (Box 1)
  - 1895 (Box 1)
  - 1896 (Box 1)
  - 1897 (Box 1)
  - 1898 (Box 1)
  - 1899 (Box 1)
  - 1900 (Box 1)
  - 1901 (Box 1)
  - February 5, 1901 (letter from former slave) (Box 1)
  - 1902 (Box 1)
  - 1903 (Box 1)
  - 1904 (Box 1)
  - 1905 (Box 1)
  - 1906 (Box 1)
  - 1907 (Box 1)
  - 1908 (Box 1)
  - 1909 (Box 1)
  - 1910 (Box 1)
  - 1911 (Box 1)
  - 1912 (Box 1)
  - 1913-1914 (Box 1)
  - 1915-1920 1948 (Box 1)
- Free Will Baptist Church, Manchester, 4 folders
  - Church records and printed material circa 1885-1912 (Box 1)
  - Committee reports circa 1885-1910 (Box 1)
  - Sunday school and young people's groups, materials circa 1885-1910 (Box 1)
  - Essays on church and religious concerns 1886-circa 1910 (Box 1)
- Other materials
  - Manchester Union school papers 1881-1906 (Box 1)
  - Southern Washtenaw Farmers' Club materials, and papers on agriculture circa 1888-1905 (Box 1)
  - Manchester Overseer of Highways papers 1907-1908 (Box 1)
  - Essays- circa 1885-1910 (Box 1)
  - Newspapers Writings and Poems circa 1885-1910 (Box 1)
  - Documents 1836, 1901-1934 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 1)
  - Postal cards 1887-1913, 1921, 1955, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook of Miss Lucy English 1885-1890 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook containing newspaper clippings concerning Southern Washtenaw Farmers' Club and Manchester local events 1887-1893 (Box 1)
  - Reports of Overseer of Highways, Manchester Township 1903-1907 (Box 1)
  - Photographs relating to American missionary work in India by members of the English family (Box 1)
- Ready Reference Books, Account books, etc.
  - Ready Reference Books, 18 volumes (Box 2)
  - Account book of Francis Baldwin 1839-1846 (Box 2)
  - Account book of Francis Baldwin 1849-1893 (Box 2)
  - Account book of Benjamin G. English 1858-1872 (Box 2)
  - Account book of Albert D. English 1887-1902 (Box 2)
  - Account book of Albert D. English 1900-1947 (Box 2)
  - Account book of John C. Mahrle 1881-1887 (Box 2)
  - Assessor's Book, Manchester School District no. 8 1871-1877, 1887-1934 (Box 2)
  - River Raisin Women's Missionary Society Treasurer's Book 1884-1896 (Box 2)
  - Composition Books undated, 1886, 3 volumes (Box 2)
  - Journal containing lecture notes on metaphysics (Box 2)
  - Personal Diary of Lucy English 1875 (Box 2)
Related Material
The Michigan State University Historical Collection also has Albert English papers.